Preliminary Guide to the Robert A. Nelson papers, 1962-1975 MS2184
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Robert A. Nelson papers
1962-1975
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Nelson, Robert, A.
MS2184
25.5 Linear Feet
Robert A. Nelson (d. March 10, 2009) was a teacher and transportation authority. He promoted high-speed rail in the Northeast corridor and is often known as "the father of the metroliner." In 1963, The Kennedy administration recurited Nelson to head the Northeast Corridor Project. This collection has material related to transportation. The collection includes studies, reports both internal and technical and, memorandum. The material dates from 1962-1975.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert A. Nelson, April 25, 1984.
Biographical Note
Robert A. Nelson (d. March 10, 2009) was a teacher and transportation authority. He promoted high-speed rail in the Northeast corridor and is often known as "the father of the metroliner." In 1963, The Kennedy administration recurited Nelson to head the Northeast Corridor Project. This project was first managed by the Commerce Department and then as part of the newly created Transporation Department. Nelson also served as a member of Lyndon Johnson's White House Task Force on Transporation Policy. In 1965, the Johnson White House created the Office of High Speed Ground Transporation. Nelson lead that office for four years. Due to his work to push railroad and manufacturer's of new railway cars, the first Metroliner demonstration trains began running in 1968. The Metroliner evolved into Amtrak's Acela.
After retiring from government service in 1969, Nelson worked as a transporation consultant. He also volunteered his expertise to many Northern Virginia transporation issues including the construction of Interstate 66 within the Beltway.
Nelson was born in Bridgewater Massachusetts. He received degrees his bachelor's degree and doctorate in economics from Clark University, and a master's degree in business from Boston University.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains primarily government reports related to various topics within the subject of high speed ground transporation including development plans, statistics, studies, and designs dating from the 1962 through 1975.
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: Geographic location, Companies, Reports, studies, and papers.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Transportation
- Geographic location, 1962-1975; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Organized into 5 subseries: Boston, Japan, Midwest and Northeast, New England, Northeast.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development within specific countries, regions, and cities.
  - Boston, 1971; Series 1 Subseries 1; 1 item(s) 1 Report (Box 1)
    Arranged chronologically
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development within Boston.
  - Japan - JNR: Japanese National Railways, 1967; Series 1 Subseries 2; 1 item(s) 1 Report (Box 1)
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development within Japan.
  - Midwest and Northeast, 1974; Series 1 Subseries 3; 2 item(s) 2 Reports (Box 1)
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development within Midwest and Northeast.
  - New England, 1963 November-1966 February; Series 1 Subseries 4; 0.75 Linear Feet 1/2 of a Record center box (Box 1)
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development within New England.
  - Northeast: Reports and loose papers, 1963-1973; Series 1 Subseries 5; 7.5 Linear Feet 5 Record center boxes
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development within the Northeast.
    - 1962-1963, Series 1 Subseries 5 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1966, Series 1 Subseries 5 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1968, Series 1 Subseries 5 (Box 3)
    - 1968-1969, Series 1 Subseries 5 (Box 4)
    - 1969, Series 1 Subseries 5 (Box 5)
    - 1970-1973, Series 1 Subseries 5 (Box 6)
- Companies, 1965-1969; Series 2
  Organized into 5 subseries: Limbaugh Engineers, Inc., Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Oceanics, Project Tubeflight, U.S. Department of Commerce
  This series contains reports produced by specific companies on various topics within the subject of high speed ground transportation.
  - Limbaugh Engineers, Inc., Series 2 Subseries 1; 0.9 Linear Feet 3/4 of a record center box
    Arranged chronologically.
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development by the company Limbaugh Engineers, Inc.
    - Limbaugh Engineers, Inc., 1968; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6)
    - Limbaugh Engineers, Inc., 1968; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), 1965-1969; Series 2 Subseries 2; 2.25 Linear Feet 1.5 Record center boxes
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development by the company Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
    - June 15, 1965-November 1966, 1965 June 15-1966 November; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 7)
    - November 1, 1966-August 15, 1969, 1966 November 1-1969 August 15; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 8)
  - Oceanics, 1967 January-1968 October; Series 2 Subseries 3; 15 item(s) 15 Reports (Box 8)
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development by project Oceanics.
  - Project Tubeflight, 1965 July-1969 January; Series 2 Subseries 4; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 Record center box (Box 9)
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development by company Project Tubeflight.
  - U.S. Department of Commerce, 1965 November 26-1968 December; Series 2 Subseries 5; 0.5 Linear Feet 1/3 of a record center box (Box 9)
    This subseries contains reports and loose paperwork related to high speed ground transportation development by company U.S. Department of Commerce.
- Reports, studies, and papers, 1962-1975; Series 3
  Arranged alphabetically
  This series contains primarily government reports and loose papers related to various topics within the subject of high speed ground transporation including development plans, statistics, studies, and designs.
  - April 15, 1962 - October 1965, 1962 April 15-1965 October; Series 3 (Box 9)
  - October 1965-July 5, 1967, 1965 October-1967 July 5; Series 3 (Box 10)
  - August 1967-January 31, 1968, 1967 August-1968 January 31; Series 3 (Box 11)
  - January 31, 1968-February 1969, 1968 January 31-1969 February; Series 3 (Box 12)
  - February 1969-April 1969, 1969 February-1969 April; Series 3 (Box 13)
  - April 30, 1969-June 1971, 1969 April 30-1971 June; Series 3 (Box 14)
  - High Speed Ground Transportation Act of 1965; reports 1-3, 1967 - 1969; Series 3 (Box 15)
  - High Speed Ground Transportation Act of 1965; reports 4-8, 1970-1974; Series 3 (Box 15)
  - Advisory Committee on High Speed Ground Transportation, 1965-1969; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Commercial Tech. Advisory Board, 1966-1967; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Committee Reports, 1961-1962; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Conference on Cybernetics, 1969-1970; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Conference of Institutional Investor - Trip to England in December, 1969; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Conference on Traffic and Transportation - Proceedings, 1957; Series 3 (Box 16)
  - Department of Transportation (DOT)/Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Study (1/3), 1964-1969; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Department of Transportation (DOT)/Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Study (2/3), 1964-1969; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Department of Transportation (DOT)/Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Study (3/3), 1964-1969; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Executive Agency Taskforce, 1962; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - General High Speed Ground Transportation Papers (1/2), 1966-1970; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - General High Speed Ground Transportation Papers, 1966-1970; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - High Speed Ground Transportation (HSGT) Contracts, 1969; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission: Department of Commerce Transporation Research Committee, 1965-1966; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission, 1965-1967; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - I.R.C.A. - U.I.C. "High-Speeds" Symposium in Vienna Booklets, 1968; Series 3 (Box 16)
  - Klauder-Budd Correspondence, 1969-1970; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Metroliner Steering Committee, 1968; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Miami Jetport, 1969; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Office of High Speed Ground Transportation (OHSGT) Staff Meetings, 1968-1969; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Mitre Memos, 1970; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Nelson, Dr. Robert A., 1963-1964; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - P-C: Passenger Case, 1970; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, n.d., undated; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Slides of Presentations, n.d., undated; Series 3 (Box 17)
  - Seminario de Transporte, 1965; Series 3 (Box 16)
  - Symposium on Short-Haul Air Transportation, 1973; Series 3 (Box 16)
  - Transparencies on various High Speed Ground Transportation topics, n.d., undated; Series 3 (Box 17)
  - Urban Transportation Task Force, 1967; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 6)